A Guide to the San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce Records, 1931-2008 (bulk 1985-2005)
San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce Records
1931-2008 (bulk 1985-2004)
San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce
MS 126
66.7 linear feet (72 boxes plus 3 oversize boxes and 1 oversize folder)
University of Texas at San Antonio Libraries Special Collections
The San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce is the oldest organization of its type in the United States, having been originally chartered by five local businessmen from Bexar County as the Mexican Chamber of Commerce on May 31, 1929. Its purpose was to encourage and promote trade and cultural relations between San Antonio and Mexico, to disseminate data and information relevant to the San Antonio business community, and to provide technical assistance to the business community in the form of seminars, workshops, and trade shows. In 1987 the Mexican Chamber was renamed the San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce. In the early 1990's the Hispanic Chamber was recognized as a critical component in negotiating the many compromises which made NAFTA possible. In recent years the chamber's role has broadened to include advocacy on behalf of small, minority- and woman-owned businesses.
The San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce Records include materials that reflect the history, work and policies of the Chamber between 1931 and 2008. Documents include correspondence, membership directories, yearbooks, bylaws, newspaper clippings, press releases, newsletters, photographs, meeting notes, reports, DVD's, a plaque, and scrapbooks.
Historical Note
The San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce is the oldest organization of its type in the United States, having been chartered on May 31, 1929, by five local businessmen from Bexar County as the Mexican Chamber of Commerce. Its purpose was to encourage and promote trade and cultural relations between San Antonio and Mexico, to disseminate data and information relevant to the San Antonio business community, and to provide technical assistance to the business community in the form of seminars, workshops, and trade shows. Its activities for membership social interaction have included dances, awards ceremonies and luncheons, business mixers, events for the Mexican Consul, celebrations of Mexican holidays, golf tournaments, banquets, and community outreach.
The Chamber was organized by Don Enrique Santibanez, Consul General of Mexico in San Antonio, who became its first president. The first meetings were held in May and June of 1928 under the sponsorship of Santibanez. Given the deep historical and commercial ties and tensions between the U.S. and Mexico, the chamber's primary emphasis in its early years was to promote trade, policy and cultural harmony. During this time, Chamber activities were characterized by efforts to develop an active network of officials and Chambers of Commerce in Mexico. The social climate and subsequent barriers to Mexican American pushed the San Antonio Chamber to go beyond the traditional scope of Chambers of Commerce, and into one of dual social and business advocacy.
In 1987 the Mexican Chamber was renamed the San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce. The name change was indicative of globalization emphasizing their relationship with all of Latin America and also the diversity of San Antonio Hispanic businesses.
The name change also set the stage for one of the greatest accomplishments for the San Antonio Hispanic Chamber. The chamber had an active alliance with Mexico's President Salinas de Gortari and Commerce Secretary Herminio Blanco to coordinate the North American Free Trade Agreement's (NAFTA) public education and promotion campaigns among Mexican-Americans in the United States. With NAFTA's passage, the Hispanic Chamber was recognized as a critical component in negotiating the many compromises which made it possible, and also as critical to its future success, again serving as the cultural and commercial connection through which many new trade deals would be realized.
The Hispanic Chamber has always provided outreach to the San Antonio community. Outspoken advocacy of educational programs, establishment of a scholarship fund, and publicly stated positions in civic matters have distinguished its contributions to the city. In recent years, guided by the fundamental belief in full participation in the free enterprise system, the chamber's role has broadened to include advocacy on behalf of small, minority- and woman-owned businesses.
Scope and Content Note
The San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce (SAHCC) Records include materials that reflect the history, work and policies of the Chamber between 1931 and 2008. Documents include correspondence, membership directories, yearbooks, bylaws, newsclippings, newsletters, legislative agendas, registers, photographs, press releases, invitations, scrapbooks and paper copies of the website. Of note is an impressive collection of photographs that document chamber board members, activities, and businesses in 20th century San Antonio. The SAHCC Records include 7 series: Administrative Files, Programs, Publicity, Events and Awards, Photographic Materials, Audiovisual and Digital Materials, and Artifacts. Additions include Addition of March 2007 (Acc. 2007-036), Addtion of May 2007 (Acc. 2007-058), Addition of March 2008 (Acc. 2008-015), and Addition of December 2008 (Acc. 2008-07).
The Administrative Files series includes bylaws, information about the history of the Chamber, and a mission statement. It also includes information about the Board of Directors, members and several committees. The correspondence includes some postcards, and a few outgoing letters, memos and an e-mail. The yearbooks provide a record of the activities and work of the Chamber throughout the year and include flyers and photocopies of color photographs from some events. Information about the Chamber's membership is found in a nearly complete run of the Hispanic Chamber Newsletter, which chronicles activities, issues, and members (1992–2003). Also available in this series are membership directories that include names and addresses of members, lists of staff and the Board of Directors, plus information about SAHCC accomplishments and a yearly calendar of events. This series also includes materials that document events planning, meetings, and government issues of note to the SAHCC.
The bulk of the Programs series documents SAHCC participation with Leadership San Antonio, a jointly sponsored program of The Greater San Antonio Chamber of Commerce and The San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce which provides a learning experience for existing and emerging leaders who live and work in the San Antonio metropolitan area. Also included in the Programs series are materials related to one-time and ongoing projects sponsored by SAHCC.
The Publicity series includes newsclippings, press releases from the Chamber office, and scrapbooks which recount the activities and work of the Mexican Chamber between 1948 and 2001. The clippings are from as early as 1950, but the bulk of the newsclippings run from 1987 to 2000. The newsclippings chronicle the activities of the Chamber from its early years as the Mexican Chamber of Commerce through its many changes, including the 1987 name change. The articles cover Chamber events and banquets, member affiliations with local businesses, and SAHCC support of local woman- and minority-owned businesses. Articles were also collected if a Chamber member was mentioned in them, or if the articles would be of interest to the Chamber and its Mexican-American audience. Included are a number of articles about the Chamber's role and support of the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA).
The Events and Awards series includes invitations and flyers about the many social and formal events sponsored by the SAHCC (bulk 1989-2000). Among these events are awards ceremonies and recognition luncheons for local businesses, business owners, and supporters of local businesses; golf tournaments; events with speakers; installation banquets for the Board of Directors; and networking mixers for members. There is also information about seminars, conferences, and programs sponsored or co-sponsored by the Chamber. Also included are materials related to event planning
Photographic Materials series includes photographs sorted by people, places and events as well as scrapbooks. The photographs provide information about Chamber members (including Board members), events, and activities within the San Antonio community. Important, older photographs include the Mexican Chamber of Commerce (1931) and a group photograph of attendees of the First Mexican Chamber of Commerce Convention (1939). Also of note is a group of oversize portraits of Board Chairs, spanning the years 1931 to 1999. Other photographs include images of events the Chamber and its members have participated in over the years; Chamber members with presidents of the United States of America and visiting foreign presidents; group photographs of Chamber members participating in events and ceremonies (including banquets, receptions and ribbon-cuttings for new businesses) (1995-2002); a series of Mexican and Mexican-American celebrities; and scrapbooks (1980-1995) in which some people and events are identified.
The Audiovisual and Digital Materials series contains various media formats including audiocassette, microcassette, CD, DVD, VHS, BetaCam, U-Matic, Zip Disks, one reel to reel and assorted digital data storage. Events covered on the recordings include speeches, award programs, interviews and news coverage.
The Additions include meeting minutes, material documenting events and award programs such as Leadership San Antonio siminars, membership directories, meeting notes, reports, CDs, DVD’s, awards, and plaques related to the San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce.
Organization of Collection
Administrative Materials
Programs
Publicity
Events and Awards
Photographic Materials
Audiovisual and Digital Materials
Artifacts
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, except original audiovisual and digital format materials, which are closed to patron use.
This collection is housed at UTSA's Main Campus and must be accessed via the John Peace Library Special Collections reading room. To request access, please use the Collections Request Form.
Acquisition Information
Materials in this collection were donated by the San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce 2004-2008 (Acc. 2004-017, 2005-029, 2005-061, 2006-095, 2006-099, 2007-036, 2007-058, 2008-015, 2008-075).
Index Terms
Organizations
San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce.; Mexican Chamber of Commerce (San Antonio, Tex.)
Subjects
Boards of trade--Texas.; Businessmen--Texas.; Mexican American organizations--Texas.; Mexican Americans--Texas--San Antonio.
Locations
Canada--Treaties, etc.--1992 Oct. 7--History.; Mexico--Relations--United States.; San Antonio (Tex.); United States--Relations--Mexico.
Genres/Formats
Audiovisual materials.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Minutes.; Programs.; Reports.; Notes.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; DVDs.; Plaque.; Awards.
Local Subjects
Business; Clubs and Organizations; Mexican Americans; Pan-Americanism
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Administrative Materials
  This series includes bylaws, information about the history of the Chamber, and a mission statement. It also includes information about the Board of Directors, members and several committees. The correspondence includes some postcards, and a few outgoing letters, memos and an e-mail. The yearbooks provide a record of the activities and work of the Chamber throughout the year and include flyers and photocopies of color photographs from some events.
  - Advertising Sales (Box 1)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, 2000 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Other Local Publications, 2001 and undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Business Development (Box 1)
    - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bylaws, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors (Box 1)
    - Members, 1950, 1988, 1994, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Resolution, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - City Proclamation, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Committees (Box 1)
    - Business Advisory and Mentoring Group (BAM), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Business Development Committee, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Governmental Affairs Committee, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - International Trade Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1946, 1950, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 2001-2002 and undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letter From John Cornyn,June 28, 2004 (Box 49)
  - Government Issues (Box 1)
    - State Legislative Agenda, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - State Legislative Agenda, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - State Legislative Agenda, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - City Governance, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - History and Mission (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Imagine…Imag?te Initiative (Box 1)
    - Brochure (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Imagine…Imag?te Initiative (Dual Language Workforce), 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Plan of Action and Newsclippings, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Miami Dual Language Workforce information, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Meeting Packets, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Membership (Box 1)
    - Applications, 1991-1998 and undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Membership Drive Brochures, 1991and undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - New Membership Packets, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Membership Directory, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Membership Directory, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Membership Directory 1995 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Membership Directory, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Membership Directory, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Membership Directory, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Membership Directory, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Membership Directory, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Membership Directory – Preparation and Planning, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Membership Directories, 2001-2003 (Box 50)
    - Leaders and Influence Database Printout (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Leaders and Influence Database Printout,1997 (Box 46)
  - Newsletters (Box 2)
    - The Alliance News, 1998, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Boletin de Comercio, May 1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Brindis (Toastmasters Monthly Bulletin), February 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chamber Update, February 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Editor, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Hispanic Chamber Business News, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, May – September 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, March – December 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – December 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – November 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – December 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – December 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – December 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – August, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, September - December, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – December 2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, May – November 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – December 2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Hispanic Chamber News, January – April 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - News Brief, June 1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, March – April, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, May – June, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, January – February, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, March – April, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, May – June, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, July – August, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, September – October, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Newsletter Preparation and Planning, November – December 2005 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - The Hispanic Chamber…Briefly Newsletter, September- November 2001 (Box 50)
    - Hispanic College Fund newsletter, July 2000 (Box 50)
    - International newsletters, 1999-2000 (Box 50)
  - Outreach – Assist Fund, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - People Files (Box 5)
    - Anastacia (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Campanas de America (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Henry Cisneros (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - La Diferenzia (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Elida y Avante (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Rosita Fernandez (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - David Lee Garza (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Oliver P. Garza (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Ruben Gomez (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Henry B. Gonzalez (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ram Herrera (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Hispanic Recipients of the National Medal of Honor (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - David Marez (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Manuel Jaramillo Rodriguez (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Nydia Rojas (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Ricardo Romo (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Presentations (Box 6)
    - Success through Partnerships/ Juntos Somos Mas (Spanish), 1997 (short form) (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Success through Partnerships/ Juntos Somos Mas (Spanish), 1997 (entire presentation) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Leading the Way to the Next Millenium/ Adelante al Futuro (Spanish), July 1998 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Leading the Way to the Next Millenium/ Adelante al Futuro (English), July 1998 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - SAHCC Information Packet, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Sponsorship – Bioscience Conference, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Staff Photos and Biographies (Box 6)
    - Tony Alvarez (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Hope Andrade (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Ines Aybar (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Frank Benitez (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Bob Bomen (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Rita Elizondo (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Arthur Rojas-Emerson (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Lewis Escareno (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Elizabeth Esquivel (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Leo Gomez (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Lorena G. Gonzales (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Heberto Gutierrez (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Heidi Hichman (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Jesse Licea (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Edward Lopez (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Anita Uribe-Martin (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Brenda Chavana Motley (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Former member personal information sheets (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Texas Association of Mexican American Chambers of Commerce (Box 7)
    - General Information, 1995and undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Trade Mission to Coahulia, Mexico (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Yearbook (Box 7)
    - Yearbook, 1985 – 1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Yearbook, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Yearbook, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Yearbook, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Yearbook, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Yearbook, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - Yearbook, 1996-1997 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - SAHCC Website, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Visitors Register, 1979-1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1996 Operating Plan, 1996 (Box 46)
  - San Antonio Bioscience Industry Profile, October 1999 (Box 47)
  - The San Antonio Hispanic Chamber of Commerce State Legislative Agenda, 2007 (Box 49)
  - 2005 Annual Report, 2005 (Box 49)
  - School Board Initiative Institute Final Report, February 8, 2006 (Box 49)
  - Directories and Contact Information, 2001-2002 (Box 49)
  - Minority Business Development Foundation Bylaws, 1995 (Box 49)
  - Y2K Contingency Plan, 1999 (Box 49)
  - Texas Association of Mexican-American Chambers of Commerce Book, 1995-1996 (Box 50)
  - Disaster Recovery Documents, 2002 (Box 50)
  - Diecis驳 de Septiembre History, undated (Box 50)
  - Courier Order Slips, undated (Box 50)
- Programs
  - Leadership San Antonio (Box 44)
    - Administrative (Box 44)
      - Directory, 1996 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio Class Days, 1999 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVI, 2000-2001 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio, 2001 (Box 44)
      - Government and Politics Day, Quality of Life, 2001-2002 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVIII, 2002-2003 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXIX, 2003-2004 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXIX, 2003-2004 (Box 45)
    - Seminars (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio XX- Crime and Punishment: Does the System Really Work?, November 2, 1994 (Box 44)
      - Health and Human Services Day, January 4, 1995 (Box 44)
      - What is "Quality of Life" in San Antonio, February 5, 1995 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio Class XXI: Crime and Punishment, November 1, 1995 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio, XXI: Government and Politics, December 6, 1995 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXI: Health and Human Services Day, January 3, 1996 (Box 44)
      - Leadership San Antonio: Government and Politics Day, December 4, 1996 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio Class XXII: Economic Development Day: Annual Report, 1996-1997 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio: Higher and Public Education, March 5, 1997 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXIII- Crime and Punishment: Juvenile Justice, November 5, 1997 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio: Health and Human Services, January 7, 1998 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXIII: Education, March 4, 1998 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXIV- Health and Human Services Day; The Many Faces of Health Care, January 9, 1999 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio- Economic Development Day: San Antonio Economic Development, April 4, 2001 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVII: Directory and Itinerary, 2001-2002 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVIII: Government Class 6, April 2, 2003 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVIII: Biomedical/ Technology Class 5, March 5, 2003 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVIII: Education, Class 3, January 8, 2003 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVIII: Economic Development, circa 2003 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXVIII: Directory, circa 2003 (Box 45)
      - Leadership San Antonio XXXI- Government Day: San Antonio Forward, January 1, 2006 (Box 45)
    - Photographs (Box 46)
  - Alexander E Briseeadership Development Program (Box 46)
    - 2001 (Box 46)
      - Alex Briseeadership Development Program: resources for Leaders,undated (Box 46)
      - Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class, 2001 (Box 46)
      - Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #1, April 2001 (Box 46)
      - Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #2, May 2001 (Box 46)
      - Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #3, June 2001 (Box 46)
      - Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #4, July 2001 (Box 46)
      - Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #5, August 2001 (Box 46)
      - Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Graduation, December 17, 2001 (Box 46)
      - Leadership Development Agenda, April 20, 2001 (Box 50)
    - 2004 (Box 46)
      - 2004 Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #1: Meyer's Briggs, April 16, 2004 (Box 46)
      - 2004 Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #2: Parliamentary Procedures, May 21, 2004 (Box 46)
      - 2004 Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #3: Conflict Resolution, June 18, 2004 (Box 46)
      - 2004 Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #4: Cross Cultural Management, July 16, 2004 (Box 46)
      - 2004 Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #5: Ethics in the Workplace, August 20, 2004 (Box 46)
      - 2004 Alexander E. Briseeadership Development Class #6: Leadership Dialogue, September 17, 2004 (Box 46)
  - Community Minority Business Advancement Program (Box 47)
    - Correspondence,2000-2001 (Box 47)
    - Press Releases and Public Relations,2000-2001 (Box 47)
    - Assorted,1997-2000 (Box 47)